10

Ongoing Personal Conflicts

In chapters 4 and 5 I related my agonising struggle with depression, and the pride that made me reluctant to acknowledge to my congregation that I had actually needed deliverance from a demon.

Also, I had always assumed that a person must be demon-free in order to minister deliverance to others. Yet I knew that someone who has been saved through faith in Christ does not have to become a perfect Christian before he or she can testify about salvation or lead others into it. In fact, the enthusiastic testimony of a new convert is often more effective than a sophisticated presentation by a mature believer.

The same can be true, I discovered, in the ministry of deliverance. People who have themselves experienced deliverance from demons are often the most successful in ministering deliverance to others, because they know from personal experience the power of the name of Jesus and the Word of God. They can also empathise with them in their struggles. Theological knowledge, on the other hand, can be more of a hindrance than a help. Deliverance is a ministry in which a person must be willing to “get his hands dirty,” dealing directly with representatives of Satan’s evil kingdom.

The basic requirement for ministering deliverance is stated by Jesus in Mark 16:17: “And these signs will follow those who believe: In My name they will cast out demons . . .” Jesus required only one thing: simple faith in His name and His Word. This is true whether one is casting demons out of others or expelling them from oneself.

Diagnosing the problems of others and helping them to be set free assisted me, paradoxically, in discerning and dealing with problems of my own. I soon learned two important principles. First, many – perhaps most – problems with demons begin in childhood. Second, if a person has persistent or intractable problems with demons, there is almost always some root in the occult. In that case, full deliverance will probably not come until this root has been exposed and dealt with.

Both of these principles applied in my own case. I was born to British parents, nominal Christians, in India, where I spent the first five years of my life. In accordance with the established custom among the British upper classes, my mother soon handed me over to a nanny, in my case a Hindu ayah, who undoubtedly became the strongest spiritual influence in my early life. I do not remember just what she did, but later, as a young boy, I often had the impression that some evil power was dogging my footsteps.

This dark influence followed me through all my early years. In my teens I formed glamorous images of India as a source of esoteric wisdom on a higher level than the materialistic culture of the West. In my student years at Cambridge, I studied yoga and even conceived an ambition to become a yogi. Had global travel been as easy then as it is now, I would doubtless have beaten a path to the door of some Indian guru.

My field of study at Cambridge was Greek philosophy, and particularly the philosophy of Plato. My two heroes at this time were Socrates and Plato. Then in World War II I had a supernatural encounter with Jesus Christ (as I mentioned in chapter 4), and this completely changed the course of my life. From then on I became an ardent student of the Bible. But much of my thinking was still influenced by Plato, and I kept some of his writings as works of reference.

As I gained further insight into the way people become exposed to demons, I saw that my admiration for Socrates and Plato kept open a door in my personality that made me vulnerable to demonic influence. Socrates himself acknowledged the influence of a demon in his life. As he was dying of the hemlock that he had been sentenced to drink, his last words to one of his associates were, “We owe a cock to Aesculapius.” He was ordering that a cock be sacrificed on his behalf to Aesculapius, the heathen god of healing.

Even though Socrates enjoys great prestige in the intellectual world, his behaviour fell into the same category as that of a man sacrificing a cock in a voodoo ceremony. Idolatry is still idolatry, even when described in elegant, classical Greek.

I realised, too, that a similar occult influence pervaded the writings of Plato, my other hero. In his last major dialogue, the Timaeus, he actually acknowledged, “We have no word from God.” So he turned to the occult literature of Egypt for revelation concerning the mysteries of the universe.

Again and again, as I sought to help those needing deliverance, I observed the close association between occult involvement and serious problems of depression. It became clear to me that this had probably contributed to my own struggles against depression when I was a young pastor.

One day in 1970 I was meditating on Deuteronomy 7:26: “Nor shall you bring an abomination into your house, lest you be doomed to destruction like it; but you shall utterly detest it and utterly abhor it, for it is an accursed thing.” I walked around my home and realised I had a number of “abominations.” So I made a decision that I believe had an important bearing on the future course of my life and ministry: I determined not to keep in my possession anything that in any way dishonoured Jesus Christ or that opened the door to demonic influence.

I rid myself of a succession of items I had inherited from my family: four antique, beautifully embroidered Chinese imperial dragons and a whole assortment of Chinese antiques, all carrying the emblem of the dragon. I also disposed of items containing elegant Arabic calligraphy, some of which undoubtedly gave glory to Mohammed and the Muslim god, Allah. I also cleared out my library, especially Plato’s books, and everything that in any way glorified the occult. Then I threw away a series of poems I had written in the days when I was still enamoured of India.

This dramatically changed the spiritual atmosphere around me. It was like passing out of twilight into the clear light of day.

I have real concern for the many Christians slow to recognise God’s intense hatred of every form of the occult. Tolerating any kind of continuing occult influence in our lives exposes us to forces that threaten our own spiritual well-being.

I remember when the TV series Bewitched brought the occult into our homes in a way that seemed amusing and harmless. Recognising its seductiveness, I warned other Christians of the danger of permitting such influences to enter their minds and spirits. Thirty years later occult programmes are proliferating on the TV screen and, in many cases, having a subtle, destructive effect on families. This is no less true of the Internet and, on a much wider scale, of movies, videos, toys and other forms of entertainment for children.

Struggling with Fear

My release from demons has been progressive, perhaps because of my occult background and heritage. At times I have still had to seek the Lord for deliverance for myself. One of the enemies that has assailed me persistently is a spirit of fear that began in my childhood. In certain circumstances I would be gripped by fear. My stomach would tighten up, my body would grow tense and sometimes my face would turn pale, even though, by the exercise of my will, I could usually maintain outward control, so that people were not aware of the struggle going on inside me.

I remember vividly when I first experienced this kind of fear. I was nine years old, sitting on the back seat of a car going too fast down a steep incline. My whole body became tense, and suddenly I felt a tingling sensation in my feet that worked its way up my legs and seemed to settle in the pit of my stomach. We did not have an accident, but a spirit of fear entered me.

After I was saved and baptised in the Holy Spirit, these attacks of fear diminished but did not altogether cease. Once I came into deliverance, I knew what to do. I would call on the Lord and He would set me free. Yet somehow I did not immediately succeed in keeping my deliverance. In moments of physical or emotional weakness, when my spiritual defences were weak, the spirit of fear would come on me unawares. As soon as I recognised its presence, I would once again claim and receive deliverance.

At first I could not understand why I should have this continuing struggle, but then I saw from the Scriptures that many of God’s strongest servants experienced an ongoing battle with fear. I thought of David, the mighty man of valour, captain of the armies of Israel. He had a close and intimate relationship with the Lord, yet he had many fears. In Psalm 34:4, for example, David says, “I sought the Lord, and He heard me, and delivered me from all my fears.”

I pondered on that phrase all my fears. Then I began to consider many different kinds of fear: fear of the dark, fear of heights, fear of man, fear of failure, fear of sickness, fear of death, fear of confined places (claustrophobia), fear of open or public places (agoraphobia), fear of the unknown. . . . A complete list would be very long. Every one of these fears is agonisingly real to the one suffering from it.

I recalled, too, Paul’s description of the troubles he encountered in Macedonia. He was attacked not only from without but also from within: “We were troubled on every side. Outside were conflicts, inside were fears” (2 Corinthians 7:5).

I would not dare to compare myself with David and Paul, two of the Lord’s most valiant servants. Nevertheless, since they struggled with fears, I did not necessarily have to write myself off as a failure because I, too, experienced such struggles.

In time I learned how to deal with this particular attack. Today, whenever I recognise the familiar symptoms of fear coming on me, I quote 2 Timothy 1:7, applying it personally: “God has not given [me] a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind [self-discipline].” Then I take my stand against the spirit of fear. When I do this, I am victorious. The spirit of fear can attack me from without, but it cannot enter me.

Essential Spiritual Conflict

This experience and others led me to rethink my concept of the Christian life. I shall always be grateful to the Christians through whom I came to the Lord in 1941. I respected their uncompromising acceptance of Scripture as the inspired, authoritative Word of God. But as I studied the Bible and encountered the problems Christians face, I realised that some of their doctrinal positions were based on human tradition, not Scripture. For instance, they often presented a simplistic picture of the Christian life: You get saved and born again, baptised in water, baptised in the Holy Spirit with the evidence of tongues – and then you have no more problems. Although not presented explicitly as a doctrine, this was the assumption behind much of their thinking.

Unfortunately, it does not correspond to the realities of the Christian life. As I have walked with the Lord, I can testify, like many others, that we never really know what spiritual problems are until we are baptised in the Holy Spirit. Only then do we begin to understand the full meaning of words such as temptation or oppression or spiritual conflict. This is no reason, however, to become discouraged. We need only look at the pattern of Jesus Himself. After the Holy Spirit came upon Him and He entered His ministry as Messiah, the Anointed One, His next experience was forty days of intense, person-to-person conflict with Satan in the wilderness.

He entered this conflict “filled with the Holy Spirit” (Luke 4:1), but He came out of it victorious over Satan, and began His public ministry “in the power of the Spirit” (verse 14). The full power of the Holy Spirit was not released even in Jesus until He had met and defeated Satan in a direct, person-to-person encounter.

The pattern Jesus set is one that each of us must follow. God releases the power of the Holy Spirit through us only in the measure that we are victorious in our spiritual conflict with Satan. It took Jesus forty days to gain His victory, but at the end it was total. We must follow the same pattern, although our victories will never be on the same level as His. We cannot bypass the conflict with Satan if we desire to see the power of the Holy Spirit released in our lives. Spiritual conflict of this kind is not the evidence of failure. Rather, it is an essential condition for fruitful ministry.

Meditating on this, I thought about my first wife, Lydia, who is now with the Lord. When I came to know her in the 1940s in what was then Palestine, she was one of the boldest and most committed Christians I had ever met. She had been a successful schoolteacher from a well-to-do family in Denmark. She left all that and came to Jerusalem in obedience to God, not knowing what He had in store for her. In 1928 she took a little dying baby girl and nursed her to health. (This story is told in my book Appointment in Jerusalem.)

For the next twenty years Lydia maintained a home for girls without parents, as a woman on her own in a culture where women are generally considered inferior. During those years she had faced riots, bandits, economic privation, primitive living conditions and opposition from Jews and Muslims, but she had never wavered. She continued that life of victory – whether in the pressures of post-war London, on a mission station in East Africa or travelling with me in ministry – right up to her death in 1975.

Yet one episode in her life surprised me. In the 1970s she and I ministered to hundreds of people needing deliverance, and we saw many glorious victories. One time after a particularly powerful session, we were returning to the apartment the church had made available to us, but Lydia refused to take the elevator. Instead she chose to walk up four flights of stairs. When I questioned her about this, she replied, “I don’t feel comfortable in an elevator.”

We talked a little more, and she recalled an incident in Denmark when she was five. She had been playing in a cupboard under the stairs in her aunt’s house, and the aunt, seeing the door open, closed and latched it. Finding herself a prisoner in the dark, Lydia became hysterical. She began to scream and pound on the door. The aunt came to her rescue quickly, but in those few moments a demon of claustrophobia – a fear of confined spaces – had apparently entered Lydia.

As soon as Lydia’s problem was brought out into the open and identified as a spirit of fear, we prayed together and she was completely delivered. She never again had a problem with elevators.

We were both astonished that Lydia herself could need deliverance after helping set so many others free. But it taught me that we need to be ready to respond to the Holy Spirit’s prompting even if it does not suit our theology! If Lydia and I had not prayed that evening, she would never have come to full victory in that area.

So I am no longer taken aback by demonic conflict even in mature Christians. I have learned, for example, to look for demonic activity in some physical infirmities. At times I have had a sore throat, cold or sinus congestion and prayed for healing with no obvious change. I would endure a week or two of frustrating infirmity before the conditions cleared up. One day, however, I was reading about the time Jesus entered the house of Simon Peter and found Peter’s mother-in-law sick with a high fever. “So He stood over her and rebuked the fever, and it left her. And immediately she arose and served them” (Luke 4:39, emphasis added). Why would Jesus rebuke a fever? Clearly He saw in that fever something more than a mere physical condition.

The next time I was fighting a feverish cold, I decided to follow the example of Jesus. I took my stand against it as a demon and received a powerful deliverance. The condition, instead of lasting a week or two, cleared up within 24 hours.

Now, when I experience pain or sickness of any kind, I consider the possibility that there is a demon behind it. If this diagnosis proves correct, complete deliverance usually follows quickly. If the problem is due to a natural physical condition, on the other hand, I pray for healing and wait on God to respond. I am also grateful for the help of doctors and medications when God leads in that way.

It would be absurd to suggest that all sicknesses are caused by demons. Some are, some are not. This makes it important to cultivate discernment, so that we can recognise which sicknesses have demonic causes and which do not. The writer of Hebrews provides a key to developing this kind of discernment: “But solid food belongs to those who are of full age, that is, those who by reason of use [margin, practice] have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil” (Hebrews 5:14).

There are two requirements, then. First, we need to feed on solid food – that is, the full revelation God has given us through the complete Bible. A thorough knowledge of Scripture is essential. Second, we must practice discerning. This is not something that will come to us only by Bible knowledge or theory. Nor does it apply only to recognising the activity of demons. It requires the consistent exercise of our spiritual senses in every situation we encounter.

The Moment of God’s Choosing

In 1994 I had a strange, unexpected experience. I was with a group of Christian intercessors, waiting on the Lord. Suddenly, without any act of my will, my hands went up into the air and my body went through a series of convulsive jerks. For a moment I felt embarrassed, wondering what the other people would think. Then I asked myself, Which is more important – what people think or what God wants to do?

I decided to yield without reservation to what God was doing. (Actually, most of the others were too preoccupied with God to notice what was happening to me.) The convulsive jerks lasted for a few minutes; then I relaxed and my body went limp. I knew I had received deliverance from a spirit, and the word stiffness came to my mind. Then God showed me when and how that spirit had gained access.

When I was born in India in 1915, the local medical facilities were relatively primitive. When I was eighteen months old, the doctor detected that my legs were unequal in length. He put one leg in a splint for several months and instructed my mother to keep me on my back. As a result I developed a stiffness in some parts of my body and an inability to make certain normal physical movements.

In the intervening nearly eighty years, I had experienced a whole series of blessings from God: salvation, the baptism in the Holy Spirit, miraculous healing, the exercise of various spiritual gifts. Yet that spirit of stiffness did not leave me until the moment God sovereignly intervened to expose it and drive it out. Now, since my deliverance, I have begun to experience new freedom of movement.

Like Lydia, my second wife, Ruth, has been an active participant with me in helping set many people free from demons. But her life, too, has not been free from demonic conflict. We have learned that God, in His sovereignty, uncovers demonic activity at times of His own choosing.

One morning about ten years ago, we had been sitting up in bed reading our Bibles, as we regularly do, when Ruth began to speak of some of the influences to which she had been exposed as a practising Jew. She related how powerfully her thinking had been affected by the humanistic element in Jewish culture. Suddenly she said, “I wonder if humanism could be a spirit.”

When Ruth renounced that spirit and commanded it to leave her, she began to shake violently. In fact, if I had not held onto her, it would have thrown her out of bed. As soon as the spirit was cast out, Ruth regained control of her body and began to praise and worship God.

What surprised us both was that something that seemed so abstract and intellectual could produce such a powerful physical reaction. As I meditated on this, I realised that humanism has its roots in Greek philosophy. It is one of the major satanic forces at work in the world today, I believe, and will ultimately open the way for the rise of the Antichrist.

From this and other experiences in the demonic realm, I have come to see that we are in a war. The more battles we win, the more we learn to recognise Satan’s tactics, and thus come closer to the full victory Jesus won for us on the cross.

I can sum up the lessons I have learned in the words of Paul in Philippians 3:12: “Not that I have already attained, or am already perfected; but I press on, that I may lay hold of that for which Christ Jesus has also laid hold of me.”

17

Will the Holy Spirit Indwell an Unclean Vessel?

The Christians who ask this question, like those who ask whether believers can ever need deliverance from demons, usually imply by their tone that the answer obviously must be No!

Contrary to many people’s thinking, however, the answer to this seventh and final question is Yes! The Holy Spirit will dwell in a vessel that is not totally clean, provided that He has been given access to the central, controlling area of human personality: the heart.

One unchallengeable example of this is provided by King David. According to the record of 2 Samuel 11, David was guilty of the sins of adultery and murder. First he committed adultery with Bathsheba; then he procured the murder of Bathsheba’s husband, Uriah. Undoubtedly David was grossly defiled by these two sins. Yet when Nathan the prophet came to confront him with his sins, he repented. Later, in bitter anguish, he prayed to the Lord, “Do not take Your Holy Spirit from me. Restore to me the joy of Your salvation” (Psalm 51:11-12).

The wording of David’s prayer is significant. He asked God to restore to him the joy of his salvation, but not to restore the Holy Spirit to him. Rather, he asked God not to take away His Holy Spirit. David had lost the joy of salvation and prayed for it to be restored, but he had never lost the presence of the Holy Spirit. Amazing as it seems, even through the sins he had committed, the Holy Spirit had remained with him.

Because God had not withdrawn His Holy Spirit, David was still able to repent. Without the Holy Spirit’s urging, he could not have repented. On the other hand, if David had rejected the Holy Spirit’s prompting, then God would almost certainly have taken the Spirit from him.

This is clear, scriptural evidence that in certain cases, the Holy Spirit will indwell an unclean vessel.

Every born-again, Spirit-filled Christian needs to thank God for this demonstration of His mercy and grace. Without it few of us would have any hope that the Holy Spirit would remain with us. Adultery or murder are not the only sins that can defile us, as Jesus made clear in Mark 7:21-23:

“For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murders, thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, licentiousness, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, foolishness. All these evil things come from within and defile a man.”

Let us focus for a moment on five of the sins in Jesus’ list: evil thoughts, covetousness, deceit, pride, foolishness. I have been associated with Christians for more than fifty years and I cannot think of one to whom I could point and say with confidence, “This person has never been guilty of any of these defiling sins.” Certainly I would not claim that for myself.

Yet God in His mercy does not take His Holy Spirit from us. He continues to indwell us, defiled though we are, but at the same time He pleads with us constantly to repent. I am grateful that the New Testament does not paint an idealistic, unrealistic picture of Christians!

The Continuous Struggle against Sin

Paul challenged Christians to a life of separation and holiness:

Therefore

“Come out from among them [unbelieving Gentiles]

And be separate, says the Lord.

Do not touch what is unclean,

And I will receive you.

I will be a Father to you,

And you shall be My sons and daughters,

Says the Lord Almighty.”

2 Corinthians 6:17-18

But immediately afterward Paul continued: “Therefore, having these promises, beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all filthiness of the flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God” (2 Corinthians 7:1).

Paul said, “Let us cleanse ourselves.” God will not do the cleansing for us. We are responsible to do it for ourselves. We must use the means of grace He has provided: We must confess our sins, repent and meet God’s conditions for forgiveness and cleansing.

Note, too, Paul’s words “Let us cleanse ourselves.” Great apostle though he was, he included himself among those who needed cleansing. Nevertheless the Holy Spirit continued to indwell Paul and the Christians to whom he was writing, even though they were not yet fully cleansed.

Paul was uncompromising about God’s standard of holiness, but equally clear that he had not yet attained it. In Philippians 3:12-15 he described his personal pursuit of holiness:

Not that I have already attained, or am already perfected; but I press on, that I may lay hold of that for which Christ Jesus has also laid hold of me. Brethren, I do not count myself to have apprehended; but one thing I do, forgetting those things which are behind and reaching forward to those things which are ahead, I press toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God in Christ Jesus. Therefore let us, as many as are mature, have this mind; and if in anything you think otherwise, God will reveal even this to you.

Each of us can do no better than follow Paul’s example: acknowledge our need of cleansing, reach out to God for it and then press on to attain the standard God has set before us.

I must emphasise that I have no intention of trying to lower God’s standards of holiness. They are forever fixed and unchangeable. But we need to be honest and realistic about the degree to which most of us have succeeded in attaining to those standards.

The teaching that every area of a person’s life must be totally clean before the Holy Spirit will indwell him may produce one of two undesirable consequences. It may deter some sincere believers from seeking the infilling of the Holy Spirit, since they say to themselves, I’ll never be able to reach that standard. Or this kind of teaching may pressure others who have received the baptism of the Holy Spirit into a form of self-righteous hypocrisy. Their reasoning goes something like this: I must have been perfect to have received the Holy Spirit, so now I’ve got to go on being perfect all the time.

The result is a make-believe Christian lifestyle. Such people still lose their tempers but now they call it righteous indignation. They still criticise their minister or their fellow Christians but they call it discernment. They still overindulge their physical appetites but they justify it by saying, “All things are lawful.”

We need to remember that the Holy Spirit is also the Spirit of truth. He is pleased when we are honest about ourselves, even though it hurts our pride. Conversely He is grieved when we hide behind a religious front.

You may ask, “Are you implying that God has no requirements for those who receive the Holy Spirit?” Certainly not! But we need to be clear as to just what they are.

The Divine Requirement

In the book of Acts we see a divine precedent: the experience of the Gentiles in the house of Cornelius who received the Holy Spirit when Peter visited them (see Acts 10:24-48). These were not Jews seeking to follow the Law of Moses. They were Gentiles, and this was probably the first time any of them had heard the Gospel. Yet the Holy Spirit fell on them and they began to speak with tongues. It would be unrealistic to think that every area of their lives had been brought into line with God’s standards by this one experience, or that they were totally free from the defilement of their Gentile background. Yet Peter commanded them to be baptised, thereby acknowledging their right to become members of Christ’s Church. Speaking of this experience later, Peter said, “[God] made no distinction between us [Jews] and them [Gentiles], purifying their hearts by faith” (Acts 15:9).

Here, then, is the essential requirement for receiving the Holy Spirit: a heart purified by faith.

Solomon counsels us, “Above all else, guard your heart, for it is the wellspring of life” (Proverbs 4:23, niv). All that we do and the way that we live spring from one source: the heart. It is characteristic of God’s practical nature that His redemptive purposes begin with the heart. Once He has purified the heart, He works outward from there with His sanctifying grace, until He has brought the whole personality under the control of His Spirit.

Does this happen immediately? Listen to Hebrews 10:14: “For by one offering [sacrifice] He [Jesus] has perfected forever those who are being sanctified.” To describe the sacrifice of Jesus, the writer uses the perfect tense: He has perfected. It is finally and forever complete. Nothing needs to be added to it and nothing can ever be taken away from it.

In describing the work of sanctification, on the other hand, the writer uses a progressive tense: They are being sanctified. Becoming holy is a stage-by-stage appropriation of what has already been made available to us by the sacrifice of Jesus. In this process the Holy Spirit (as His title indicates) is our Helper.

The Holy Spirit is realistic about our failings. He gently points out our mistakes and sins, and helps us to change. At times He may powerfully convict us, but He never condemns us.

This realism about the continual struggle of Christians against sin is presented forcefully in the New Testament. In Hebrews 3:13 the writer says: “Exhort one another daily . . . lest any of you be hardened through the deceitfulness of sin.” Again in Hebrews 12:1 the writer speaks about “the sin which so easily ensnares us.” And in verse 4 he says, “You have not yet resisted to bloodshed, striving against sin.”

Dealing with sin is a life-and-death struggle. It is not shameful to acknowledge that sin is still at work in our lives. On the contrary, our great danger lies in refusing to acknowledge it, which leaves us unprepared to resist temptations when they do come.

If the Holy Spirit were to wait until we are perfect to take up His dwelling within us, it would be like a professor saying to his students, “I’ll start teaching you when you have passed your exams.” His students would respond, “But professor, that’s not what we need! We need you to start teaching us now, so we’ll learn what we need to pass our exams.”

It is now that we need the Holy Spirit, so that we may have His help available to us continually to overcome the power of evil and to attain to God’s standard of holiness. One particular area of conflict in which we need the Holy Spirit’s help is in dealing with demons. The Holy Spirit does not withhold His help if He discerns that there are demons within us. On the contrary, He sees our need more clearly than we do ourselves, and He empowers us to expel them. Because He has compassion on us, He is willing to take up His dwelling within us, and to work with us to establish Christ’s victory over all the power of the enemy. Our progress depends on the degree to which we co-operate with the Holy Spirit within us.

Let me emphasise once again: The Holy Spirit does not come to indwell us because we are already perfect. He comes to help us so that we may become perfect.

Certainly the Holy Spirit will not help us in our struggle with demons if we intend to continue living in sin. But if we recognise our sins and sincerely repent, He will fight with us against the demons that enslave us. With His help we will be able to expel them and be set free.

Cleansing the Vessel

In the testimony that follows, a congressional aide in Washington, D.C., speaks frankly of her personal struggles:

I was baptised in the Spirit about seven years ago. In late June of last year, in a church in Washington, D.C., I received an instant healing of nerve deafness. Then in August my doctor confirmed that I was healed of cysts and tumours in the breasts.

I was top staff member for a Congressman and, while he personally was thrilled with my experience of healing, my testimony was not well received in the political circles in which I moved. In September I resigned from my job and spent the next few months resting and taking time with the Lord.

Then in mid-December I became depressed and despondent. The first week of January was horrible! One day I lost my temper. I was here all alone, and it related to a most trivial matter. I realised instantly the sin I had committed – anger. And as I tried to pray for forgiveness in English, I felt choked . . . not from emotions, but a distinct pressure on my throat – a very real physical force.

A friend suggested that I might need deliverance. So I bought your tapes dealing with deliverance and demonology.

I have always shied away from anything concerning spirits, demons, ghosts and what-have-you, believing that if I left them alone, they would surely leave me alone. I just did not want any truck with spirits and demons! Still, I listened to your tapes on deliverance. I had my Bible on the table and kept pace as you followed through the Scriptures. At the end of the tape, when you gave the instructions to your class, I decided to follow also. Then you started the prayer for deliverance, but the tape ended abruptly – and almost the last thing you said on the tape is, “Remember, Jesus is your Deliverer.”

I did not know what to expect or what to do. So my prayer to the Lord was that I didn’t know what to do, but that since He was my Deliverer, I was committing myself completely to Him. I named those things not of the Lord that I felt were evil and sinful and which I did not want to be part of me – resentment, unforgiveness, doubts, anxieties, fears, etc.

As I have said, I didn’t know what to expect. Within a very few minutes, not more than two or three, I began to heave and gag in the most desperate kind of way. After about ten minutes or so, I felt that my abdominal region would never be the same! But I did not feel or believe that I was completely released. Then I asked the demons or spirits to name themselves and I commanded them to come out. This did not happen. Why, I don’t know.

Then I asked the Lord to tell me if there were more, and what the names were, so I could ask deliverance from them. The first one was suicide, and the force was something terrific. I felt it all the way to the top of my head. I felt some release, but not completely. I asked the Lord to tell me if there were more – and I was told it was the deaf spirit. The deliverance of that was fantastic! It lasted longer than anything else, and the force actually pulled my abdomen to my back, and I physically felt the violent uprooting of my stomach, and in this also I felt the pressure in my head.

I am completely released, and ever since have known such a marvellous peace.

24

Why Some Are Not Delivered

Most of the people who have prayed the prayer outlined in chapter 22 have received deliverance from demons – but not all.

Here are ten possible factors that might hinder a person from receiving deliverance:

Lack of repentance
Lack of desperation
Wrong motives
Self-centredness – a desire for attention
Failure to break with the occult
Failure to sever binding soulish relationships
Lack of release from a curse
Failure to confess a specific sin
Not “separated” by water baptism
Part of a larger battle

1. Lack of Repentance

Jesus began His public ministry with the words “Repent, and believe” (Mark 1:15). He never expected anyone to believe without first repenting. Faith that does not proceed out of repentance is not valid and cannot be expected to produce the results promised to true faith.

Every sinner is, by both act and nature, in rebellion against God. We do not qualify to receive God’s blessings until we have renounced our rebellion and turned totally away from it. This is the essential nature of repentance: renouncing our rebellion against God. Ask yourself, Am I submitted without reservation to the authority of Jesus Christ in my life? If you cannot answer yes, you are still in an attitude of rebellion. There is only one remedy: repentance.

In repentance, we submit ourselves by an act of the will to the Lordship of Christ in our lives. Our repentance is proved genuine when we go on to study and obey the teachings of Jesus.

People often seek deliverance because they want to be free from the unpleasant consequences of demonic oppression. But this is not sufficient reason. If you do not commit yourself to go on after deliverance to serve the Lord, either you will not receive deliverance at all, or if you do receive it, it will not be permanent.

2. Lack of Desperation

When we are seeking deliverance from Satan’s bondage, we need to recognise the reality of our situation. We have been taken prisoner by a cruel despot who hates us with total hatred and will do everything he can to harm us and, if possible, to destroy us. When we turn to Christ for deliverance, it must be with the recognition that He is the only One who can help us.

We need to be as desperate as Peter was when he was sinking in the waters of Galilee and cried out to Jesus, “Lord, save me!” (Matthew 14:30). He realised that in another moment the water would close over his mouth and he would no longer be able to cry for help.

Several times, when a person has approached me seeking deliverance, I have said, “Deliverance is for the desperate. I don’t feel that you are desperate yet. Come back when you are.” Sometimes I suggest that a person fast for 24 hours before seeking deliverance.

3. Wrong Motives

The apostle James, analysing reasons that people sometimes pray but do not get what they pray for, wrote, “You ask and do not receive, because you ask amiss, that you may spend it on your pleasures” (James 4:3).

This often applies to people praying for deliverance from demons. They have come to recognise that demonic bondage is, in varying degrees, unpleasant and frustrating. It is a barrier to their pleasures. They think they could get more enjoyment out of life if they were set free.

But this is not sufficient reason for God to respond to their prayers. When we come to Him for deliverance, He searches our motives. He offers freedom to those who will use it to serve Christ more effectively, not those who wish to continue in a life of selfish pleasure.

4. Self-Centredness – A Desire for Attention

Some people always feel ignored and unimportant. They want to be at centre stage but life keeps them in the background. They feel nobody cares about them. One possible reason: They are oppressed and suppressed by demons.

When they seek deliverance, they suddenly find themselves the centre of attention and they enjoy it. But after some measure of deliverance, they drop back into the shadows. People no longer pay as much attention to them. So they find some new aspect of their “problem” to discuss and some new area in which they need deliverance. Deep down they really do not want to be free. What they want is attention. They are like the women described by Paul in 2 Timothy 3:7, “always learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.”

It is right to have compassion on such people and to present clearly the conditions for receiving deliverance. But there comes a point when we must challenge them to accept full deliverance – and the responsibility that goes with it, as outlined in chapter 21.

5. Failure to Break with the Occult

It is seldom easy to make a full and final break with the occult. Satan will use every trick in his repertoire to hold onto his victims. A person seeking to break away may be like Lot’s wife escaping from Sodom. She turned around for one last, regretful look at what she was leaving behind and became forever immobilised as a pillar of salt (see Genesis 19:26). Jesus held her up as a warning to all succeeding generations: “Remember Lot’s wife” (Luke 17:32).

The land of Canaan into which God brought the Israelites was corrupted by idolatry and occult involvement. For this reason God told His people, “Do not bow down before their gods or worship them or follow their practices. You must demolish them and break their sacred stones to pieces” (Exodus 23:24, niv). The Israelites were required to obliterate every trace of occult involvement. Nothing was to be carried over from the old order to the new. God even demanded that His people’s speech indicate the total break with the old order: “Make no mention of the name of other gods, nor let it be heard from your mouth” (Exodus 23:13).

The world around us today is like the land of Canaan at that time – corrupted and defiled by every conceivable form of the occult. But many Christians, as I said earlier, are slow to recognise how intensely God hates the occult. He requires that we make the same total break with all those things that He required of Israel in the land of Canaan: We must obliterate every trace of them from our lives.

The things that link us to the occult are often subtle and hard to detect. A person seeking deliverance needs to pray, “Lord, show me if there is anything in my life that still links me to the occult, and show me how to make a complete break.”

6. Failure to Sever Binding Soulish Relationships

In chapter 15 I pointed out that demonic bondage can result from being manipulated or controlled by soulish pressure exercised by some other person. Release from such bondage obviously depends on severing any such controlling relationship.

Jesus warned us that “a man’s foes will be those of his own household” (Matthew 10:36). This is often true in cases of such binding personal relationships. A mother, for instance, may seek to control her child. Or a young man may continually be pressured by his brother to go back to taking drugs with him.

No matter how close the family member or friend, full freedom will not come until that control is severed. The process of adjusting such relationships may be painful, but it is essential for full deliverance. Sometimes it is necessary to break all contact with the controlling person and trust God to re-establish the relationship in His time and on His terms. When this is not possible (as in the case of a spouse or a child living at home), the person seeking to stay free must be vigilant to avoid coming back under that familiar controlling power.

7. Lack of Release from a Curse

In chapter 21 I listed seven common indicators that there may be a curse over a person’s life. If you recognise that any of the forces I identified are still at work in your life, it may be that you are not yet fully released from every curse.

The basis of your release is the exchange that took place at the cross. There Jesus took on Himself every curse to which our sinfulness had exposed us, that in return we might be entitled to every blessing due to His spotless righteousness.

The ramifications of this exchange are many-sided and extend into every area of our lives. For a comprehensive treatment of this subject, I direct you to my book Blessing or Curse: You Can Choose!

8. Failure to Confess a Specific Sin

“If we confess our sins, [God] is faithful and just to forgive us our sins. . .” (1 John 1:9). God does not necessarily require that we confess individually every sin we have ever committed. But at times one specific sin must be brought out into the open. Until it is acknowledged and confessed, God withholds His forgiveness and cleansing.

After David was convicted of his sins of adultery and murder, he said, “My sin is ever before me” (Psalm 51:3). David recognised the horror of the sin that had separated him from God. His only hope for inward peace and renewed fellowship with God was to bring his sin out into the open by specific confession.

When a person is seeking deliverance from demons, there may be a specific sin that has to be confessed. It may be the sin that opened him or her up to the demon in the first place. In that case God will withhold deliverance until the particular sin has been identified and confessed.

A mother once brought her teenage daughter to Lydia and me for deliverance. We succeeded in casting out a number of demons, but there was one stuck in the girl’s throat that refused to move any further.

Eventually I said to the young woman, “I believe you have committed one specific sin that God requires you to confess by name.”

The girl looked at me for a few moments in acute embarrassment, then blurted out, “I had an abortion.”

The mother let out a gasp. She had apparently known nothing about it.

“God requires one more thing,” I told the young woman. “You have to confess that abortion as murder.”

She did. And the moment she correctly named her sin as murder, she was completely delivered. She received forgiveness not only from God but from her mother. Mother and daughter fell into each other’s arms and cried together.

When God requires the confession of some specific sin, we must rely on the Holy Spirit to reveal it. It is His ministry, after all, to convict of sin (see John 16:8). In addition to murder, specific sins that often need to be confessed are listed in the last four of the Ten Commandments: adultery, theft, false witness and coveting (Exodus 20:14-17).

9. Not “Separated” by Water Baptism

Being baptised in water, as I pointed out in the last chapter, is the outward act by which we “complete” the salvation we have received through our faith in Christ’s atonement. A person who has believed but not been baptised is “incompletely” saved. It is only “complete” salvation that grants us the legal right to be free from demonic oppression. Unfortunately, even some churches that practice baptism by immersion do not sufficiently emphasise its importance.

I want to make clear, however, that I am not speaking of baptism as a ceremony required to join some particular congregation, but simply as an act of personal obedience to Scripture. Whenever I pray for deliverance with people who have never been baptised as believers, I warn them, “You are free now, but if you intend to retain your freedom, you must be baptised in water.”

On the other hand, you may have done this without understanding the complete deliverance from Satan’s power to which you are legally entitled. If you still find yourself harassed by Satan’s demons, take your stand on what your baptism really means. Pray something like this: “Lord Jesus, I thank You that I have passed through the water out of Satan’s kingdom and into Your Kingdom. And now, Lord, I take authority in Your name and cut off every harassing demon that has been pursuing me.”

10. Part of a Larger Battle

As Christians we are involved in a vast spiritual war that spans both earth and heaven. Paul describes this as a wrestling match against satanic forces in the heavenlies (see Ephesians 6:12). At times we may find ourselves in conflict not only with demons on the earthly plane, but also with daimons (see chapter 11) whose headquarters are in the heavenlies.

Sometimes a person who appears relatively unimportant on the earthly plane is a strategic element in this global conflict. Satan’s daimons are aware of this and are determined to retain control over that life and use it to oppose God’s purpose. Consequently, any attempt to minister deliverance is resisted fiercely, not only by the demons in the person but also by the satanic forces in the heavenlies operating through that person. I call such a person a “battleground.”

A single individual, for instance, may be the key to the salvation of a whole family or even some larger community. Or the deliverance of just one person may open the door to bring the Gospel to a hitherto unreached people group. If this is so, Satan will marshal his forces, both on earth and in the heavenlies, to retain his control over that individual.

To minister to such people, we need insight into the heavenlies – perhaps through a vision or word of wisdom or knowledge. If we have a clear picture of the forces opposing us, we can call on committed intercessors to stand together with us to claim the victory Christ has gained for us. For through His atoning death and victorious resurrection, He has “disarmed principalities and powers” of Satan that oppose us (Colossians 2:15).

It may also be, when a person does not receive deliverance, that we need to apply the words of Jesus in Mark 9:29: “This kind can come out by nothing but prayer and fasting.”

25

Helping Others Be Set Free

People who have been delivered from demons often begin to see clearly the need for others to receive similar deliverance. Also, they can empathise with them because they remember the pressures to which they were subjected and the struggles involved in the process of being delivered. As a result, many find themselves spontaneously reaching out to others who also need deliverance.

In Mark 16:17 Jesus opened up this ministry to all believers: “And these signs will follow those who believe: In My name they will cast out demons . . .”

As a general principle, however, deliverance should be practised primarily by people with apostolic, pastoral or evangelistic ministries, or their co-workers. But any Christian confronted by a demonized person may in certain circumstances be called on to cast out demons. I have seen in experience, however, that people who engage in a regular ministry of deliverance without observing certain scriptural conditions for exercising authority usually end up in trouble.

Here are some general principles that can safeguard the practice of deliverance:

Be under authority
Two are better than one
Do not minister alone to a member of the opposite sex
Use the cross and the sword of the Spirit

1. Be under Authority

At one point in His ministry, Jesus sent out seventy disciples to prepare the way before Him. They returned with great excitement, reporting that “even the demons are subject to us in Your name” (Luke 10:17). Jesus responded, “Behold, I give you the authority … over all the power of the enemy” (verse 19). The decisive factor in dealing with demons is the exercise of scriptural authority.

A Roman centurion who came to Jesus on behalf of his sick servant recognised that Jesus’ spiritual authority was comparable to his own military authority. He summed up in one sentence the essential condition for exercising authority in any sphere: “Say the word, and my servant will be healed. For I also am a man placed under authority. . .” (Luke 7:7-8). To exercise authority, a person must first be under authority.

There are certain scriptural principles that govern the exercise of authority.

First, the supreme source of all authority is God Himself. After the resurrection, however, Jesus declared to His disciples, “All authority has been given to Me in heaven and on earth” (Matthew 28:18). This means that all authority descends from God the Father through Jesus the Son. To be under scriptural authority, therefore, every Christian needs to find his or her place in a chain of authority that stretches upward through Christ to God.

In 1 Corinthians 11:2-7 Paul uses covering the head as a symbol of authority. To be under authority is to be “covered” – that is, protected. Not to be under authority is to be “uncovered” – that is, unprotected. For every Christian, therefore, to be under an appropriate form of authority is to be spiritually protected. A Christian not under authority is spiritually unprotected and is in great danger.

God has made Christ “head over all things to the church, which is His body” (Ephesians 1:22-23). It is natural, therefore, for Him to exercise His authority in any area through the leadership of a local church. This means that a Christian who desires to be protected spiritually should take his or her place in the structure of a local church.

Ruth and I attach great importance to this issue of authority. Wherever we reside, we make ourselves part of a local congregation and come under its leadership. When we go out on ministry trips, we are sent out from our local church. In addition, our world-wide ministry is directed by an International Council in which we share leadership with a group of our co-workers who represent the various countries in which they minister. For my part, I always make it plain that I have no desire to be independent. On the contrary, I gladly recognise that I am dependent – first and foremost on God, then on the people of God.

One other main area in which God delegates His authority is the family. In 1 Corinthians 11:3 Paul depicts a chain of authority descending from God, through Christ, into every family on earth: “But I want you to know that the head of every man is Christ, the head of woman is man, and the head of Christ is God.”

A married woman is normally under the authority of her husband and should not be engaged in ministering without her husband’s full knowledge and approval. Peter warns us, however, that if there is not harmony between husband and wife, the husband’s prayers will be hindered (see 1 Peter 3:7). An unmarried woman, if still at home, needs her father’s authorisation. Single women living on their own should have the authorisation and oversight of mature spiritual leaders.

Men who practice deliverance, whether single or married, should be part of a fellowship or church with an effective structure of authority. This whole area of dealing with demons is a dangerous place for “lone rangers,” whether male or female.

There is one key word in the question of being under authority: accountable. Each Christian needs to ask, To whom am I accountable? A person not accountable to anyone is not under authority.

In two places Jesus speaks about authority to bind and to loose. In each case it is in relationship to the Church. In Matthew 16:18–19 Jesus says to Peter, “. . .On this rock I will build My church . . . and whatever you [singular] bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven.”

Again in Matthew 18:17-18 Jesus is speaking about bringing an offending brother before the Church, and He concludes, “Whatever you [plural] bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven.” In this case binding and loosing is a collective action of the Church as a whole.

The key to the scriptural exercise of all authority is right relationships. This applies specifically to binding and loosing demonic forces. A person who is not in a right relationship to the Body of Christ may attempt to bind or loose demons, but the authority to make it effective will be lacking.

2. Two Are Better than One

There is no record in the gospels that Jesus ever sent anyone out to minister by himself. He always sent out His disciples in pairs. Normally only an experienced minister with authority should undertake the ministry of deliverance on his own. (Bear in mind, there is always the possibility that a person receiving deliverance may become violent.)

This principle is emphasised by Solomon in Ecclesiastes 4:9-10:

Two are better than one,

Because they have a good reward for their labour.

For if they fall, one will lift up his companion.

But woe to him who is alone when he falls,

For he has no one to help him up.

3. Do Not Minister Alone to a Member of the Opposite Sex

It is unwise for a woman to attempt to minister to a man on her own, or for a man to minister to a woman on his own. Generally the best team for this ministry is a married couple working in harmony.

In each of my two marriages God has blessed me with a wife with whom I have lived in harmony and who worked at my side every time I ministered deliverance. I owe much to the special contributions of Ruth, and Lydia before her – a word of knowledge, a gift of healing or discerning of spirits. During the period of three years between my first and second marriages, while I was a widower, I never counselled a woman alone. I was always careful to have the support and help of a mature and competent brother or sister in the Lord.

4. Use the Cross and the Sword of the Spirit

There is one – and only one – all-sufficient basis on which anyone can claim deliverance from demons: the substitutionary sacrifice of Jesus on the cross. By this He made atonement for the sins of the whole human race and stripped Satan of his primary weapon against us: guilt. By faith in this sacrifice, each one of us is justified, acquitted, “just-as-if-I’d never sinned.”

Lay hold of this truth and make it central in all your instruction to those you are helping.

Likewise, there is only one weapon that is invariably effective in dealing with demons. It is the sword of the Spirit – the words of Scripture spoken boldly and in faith. Demons are not frightened by denominational labels, ecclesiastical titles or theological arguments. But against the sharp sword thrust of God’s Word, spoken in faith, demons have no defence.

Final Practical Points

If you are preparing to minister to someone who needs deliverance, here are twelve practical points to help make your ministry more effective. For the sake of brevity, I will refer to the person receiving deliverance as “the counsellee,” and I will use masculine pronouns that may apply to either sex.

Reread chapter 21 of this book and, insofar as possible, take the counsellee through the nine preliminary steps.
Let the sacrifice of Jesus on the cross be the basis of all you do. Likewise, encourage the counsellee to look away from himself and focus on the cross.
Check for the following three critical issues:
Repentance: Has the counsellee gone through a genuine experience of repentance, as defined earlier?
Forgiveness: Is there anyone whom the counsellee has not truly forgiven? Is he still holding resentment against anyone?
Renunciation: Has the counsellee totally renounced every contact with the occult and/or every binding personal relationship?
If the counsellee is struggling, do not simply take over and do it all for him. Suggest appropriate Scriptures for him to quote on his own behalf. Encourage him to exercise and develop his own faith. This will help him face any further conflicts with Satan.
Sometimes the process of deliverance may encounter a kind of spiritual “logjam” in which the counsellee appears to be struggling against something in himself that he does not fully understand. If this happens, ask the Lord for a word of knowledge that will identify the nature of the problem. This word of knowledge may come either to the counsellee or to the one ministering. It may concern a sin that must be confessed or a binding power that must be broken (for example, a false religion). To proceed further, the counsellee must repent of the sin or break the binding power. Alternatively, the Holy Spirit may reveal the name of a certain demon resisting the deliverance. If so, instruct the counsellee to take his stand in the name of Jesus and renounce that particular demon by name.
Demons often come out through the mouth with sobbing, crying, screaming, roaring, spitting or even vomiting. Have a supply of tissues or paper towels or other similar materials ready that the counsellee can use.
A woman sometimes expels demons with loud screaming. If she continues to scream without receiving any further deliverance, remember that a demon may have lodged itself in the narrow part of her throat and be holding on there. Explain this to the woman and instruct her to expel the demon from her throat with a deliberate, forceful cough (see chapter 21).
Do not shout at demons. They are not deaf. Even a spirit of deafness is not deaf. Shouting at them does not give you more authority; it only uses strength that could be better spent in other ways.
Do not waste time on attention-getters – people who go through some of the actions of a person receiving deliverance but are interested only in attracting attention to themselves (see chapter 24).
As you minister, Satan may attack you with a spirit of fear. If so, affirm that “God has not given [me] a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind”
(2 Timothy 1:7). Remember, too, the promise Jesus gave His disciples when they had to deal with demons: “Nothing shall by any means hurt you” (Luke 10:19).
Continually emphasise the promise of Joel 2:32: “Whoever calls on the name of the Lord shall be saved [delivered].”
Remember the power in the name of Jesus and the blood of Jesus. Here is a proclamation I have used many times (taken from my book Prayers and Proclamations) to enable Christians to apprehend and possess the victory Jesus won for us on the cross:

We overcome Satan when we testify personally

to what the Word of God says

the blood of Jesus does for us:7

Through the blood of Jesus

I am redeemed out of the hand of the devil.8

Through the blood of Jesus

all my sins are forgiven.9

Through the blood of Jesus

I am continually being cleansed from all sin.10

Through the blood of Jesus

I am justified, made righteous, just-as-if-I’d

never sinned.11

Through the blood of Jesus

I am sanctified, made holy, set apart to God.12

Through the blood of Jesus

I have boldness to enter the presence of God.13

The blood of Jesus cries out continually

to God in heaven on my behalf.14

Each person ministering deliverance will discover other practical points. But theory can take us only so far. In the end we all have to learn by doing. I hope this book will help you avoid some of the mistakes I have made!

One final word of great importance. It was love that motivated God to provide deliverance for us through the sacrificial death of Jesus. Our motivation should be the same. Ask God, therefore, to make you an instrument of His love: “Let all that you do be done with love” (1 Corinthians 16:14).

7. Revelation 12:11, 8. Ephesians 1:7, 9. 1 John 1:9, 10. 1 John 1:7, 11. Romans 5:9, 12. Hebrews 13:12, 13. Hebrews 10:19, 14. Hebrews 12:24